A Guide to the Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)
The Library of Virginia
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-001-1919-001
Digital images
Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Madison County was named for James Madison, a Virginian statesman, author of the United States Constitution, and member of Congress when the county was formed from Culpeper County by a statute adopted on 4 December 1792. This was the second Virginia county to be named for future president Madison. The county court first met on 23 May 1793. The county seat is Madison.
Scope and Content
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913), are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, business records, or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Madison County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
See the Chancery Records Index to search for chancery suits of additional Virginia localities.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Business enterprises--Virginia--Madison County.; Debt--Virginia--Madison County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Madison County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Madison County.; Equity--Virginia--Madison County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Madison County.
Geographical Names:
Madison County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Madison County.; Deeds--Virginia--Madison County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Madison County.; Land records--Virginia--Madison County.; Local government records--Virginia--Madison County.; Plats--Virginia--Madison County.; Wills--Virginia--Madison County.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1803-003, Exrs. Of Robert Beverley vs. Mackenzie Beverley
  Contains will of Robert Beverley, Sr., Essex Co., builder of Blandfield Plantation. Frees enslaved personal attendant and "his wife."
- 1818-002, Simon B. Chapman vs. John Wright, etc.
  Suit concerns a contract for substitute militia service and discusses some generalities about the War of 1812.
- 1822-005, James P. Sims vs. William Jarrett, etc.
  Suit initiated because Jarrett was accused of murder by coroner's inquest and flees county. By law, coroner took possession of Jarrett's property and Sims sues to get title to land he paid Jarrett for.
- 1823-017, Mary Clark vs. William Davis, Asgn.
  Suit references plaintiff boarding with defendant and raising several "young Negroes" for him.
- 1830-005, Joseph Good vs. J. B. Norton, etc.
  Suit invovles a patent dispute over rights to improvements to Bergen's self-sharpening plow.
- 1837-007, Moses~, etc. vs. Exr. of John Stockdell
  The plaintiffs, who were slaves, sued because Stockdell's will called for them to be turned over to American Colonization Society for transport to Liberia (with funds from estate for passage.) Executors continued to rent out the slaves even though there are no debts owed by estate. The court ruled in favor of the plaintiffs.
- 1839-004, Joseph Hume vs. Exrs. Of Joseph Clark, etc.
  Includes a genealogical chart and extensive explanation of familial relationships of whole and half-blood.
- 1844-008, Henry Hill vs. Humphrey Taylor
  Hill and Taylor were business partners engaged "in the business of buying slaves in the state of Virginia … and selling in the southern part of the United States," specifically Mississippi and Louisiana. After the partnership dissolved, Hill sued Taylor to recover his fair share of the partnership's profits. Hill asked the court to perform an audit of all the partnership's transactions from the time of its commencement to its dissolution. Documents found in the suit such as Hill's complaint, Taylor's rebuttal, depositions, affidavits, commissioners' reports, and correspondence provide a "behind the curtain" look into the slave trade. Even more significant are the lists containing the names of hundreds of slaves who were bought in Virginia and sold in Mississippi and Louisiana by Hill and Taylor from 1830 to 1843 (See image numbers 172-189, 194, 206-211). The lists record the names of slaves, purchase price in Virginia, sale price in Mississippi and Louisiana, the date of sale, and the names of individuals who purchased the slaves.
- 1844-014, Nathaniel Tatum, etc. vs. William H. Twyman, etc.
  Suit involves slave traders.
- 1854-011, William J. Carpenter, etc. vs. Admr. of Thomas Shirley, etc.
  The suit concerns the will of a woman under "fanatical influence of Shakers [sect]" who renounced her inheritance of a slave from Thomas Shirley.
- 1867-010, Jacob G. Weast, etc. vs. Admr. of Benjamin Burton
  Plaintiff found substitute for defendant in CSA Army ca. 1861 and was promised 500 dollars in three payments. The plaintiff collected one payment and dies. The plaintiff sued for remainder. The administrator contends that debt is invalid because it concerns service for the CSA, and the only true government of Virginia was the Restored Government now back in place in Richmond. The argument failed; the court ruled in favor of the plaintiff.
- 1891-032, Exrs. of Charles Hume vs. Hannah Sparks, etc.
  Suit concerns the settlement of Charles Hume's estate. Hume died in 1860 and provided in his will for "two old negroes" Charles and Hay (later referred to as Hay Taliaferro). Charles dies before or shortly after Hume. There is some question as to an agreement between Hay and Hume's executors regarding his care and maintenance. Hay, a petitioner to the suit, claims to have been duped by the executors into signing an agreement that was not to his benefit. A decree from the Supreme Court of Appeals in the suit seems to imply that Hay has no standing in the suit since he was freed at the end of the Civil War.
- 1919-001, Adms. Of Thomas Shirley vs. Heirs of Thomas Shirley and Zachariah Shirley vs. Adms. Of Thomas Shirley
  The suit began in 1840's and continued to early 20th century. It was an estate dispute, so there is extensive genealogical information and slave relationships and occupations. The suit also includes letterhead depicting a political cartoon relative to the 1844 Presidential race.